<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The true news of the good new world shortly to come (Heb. 2. 5.) for all such as then shall be found real saints with the sudden end of all the enjoyments of this present evil world ...</title>
            <author>Sherwin, William, 1607-1687?</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1675</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 96 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 14 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A59944</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing S3412</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R34239</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">14153634</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 14153634</idno>
            <idno type="VID">102127</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A59944)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 102127)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1070:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The true news of the good new world shortly to come (Heb. 2. 5.) for all such as then shall be found real saints with the sudden end of all the enjoyments of this present evil world ...</title>
                  <author>Sherwin, William, 1607-1687?</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 12 p., 4 folded leaves of plates : charts.  </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London? :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1675?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed by Wing to Sherwin.</note>
                  <note>Imprint suggested by Wing.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Union Theological Seminary Library, New York.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Revelation --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Second Advent.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Zev Berger</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:102127:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:102127:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE TRUE NEWS OF THE <hi>GOOD NEW WORLD</hi> (Shortly) to come, [<hi>Heb.</hi> 2.5.] for all ſuch as then ſhall be found real Saints.</p>
            <p>WITH THE SUDDEN END OF ALL THE <hi>Enjoyments of this preſent Evil WORLD,</hi> To ſuch as then ſhall be found Unſanctified, Tender'd to the ſerious con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of all ſorts
<list>
                  <item>in a Divine Scheme at 6 <hi>d.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>or a little Book with it at 12 <hi>d.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>To be briefly explained (to all that are willing to hear) in any convenient Time or Place to be appointed, without juſt cauſe of fear or ſhame [as the Compiler thereof lately Petitioned the Kings Majeſty, and more lately the Lord Mayor and Court of Aldermen of this City] according to the Word of God, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But ſuch Perſons as appear to be indigent, [whoſe Names may be ſet down, to uſe the ſaid Scheme a Week for 1 <hi>d.</hi> or the Book for 2 <hi>d.</hi> until they be explained,] may have them, returning them unimpair'd: or (haply for nothing).</p>
         </div>
         <div type="summary">
            <pb facs="tcp:102127:2"/>
            <head>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> great benefits of the right knowledge of our Saviours main ſcope in the four last Chapters of the Revelation, largely explained in Reſur. on Rev. <hi>20.5.</hi> and Reſtit. on Rev. <hi>21.5.</hi> are theſe, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <p n="1">I. THereby an excellent Guidance it obtained, to underſtand and diſtinguiſh the meaning and intent of ancient Propheſie, both concerning Chriſt himſelf, and his Saints, before and ſince his firſt coming, and what concerns both himſelf and them in that ſtate following his ſecond coming [as <hi>Introduct. pag.</hi> 14. <hi>col.</hi> 2.] which to cut off as Unſcriptural, is a great and manifold Errour, as is manifeſt from the whole current of ſacred Scriptures and without the acknowledgment thereof, not only ancient Propheſie of the Old Teſtament, but many places in the Goſpels, and the Apoſtles Writings both upon the foundations of thoſe Propheſies, and tending to Chriſts own ſaid Explication of that following ſtate, are not, yea and they cannot be rightly underſtood; being the very ſubject thereof: which much concerns all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians now to know and conſider well, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">II. Thereby the moſt full, true Scriptural Explications of theſe three following Articles of our uſual Creed are now only attainable [except by New Revelation, which is not to be expected.]</p>
            <p n="1">1. That Chriſt will ſo come from the Fathers right hand to judge the quick, <hi>viz.</hi> his great and leſſer Enemies by a temporal deſtruction of them, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 39.8. <hi>Matth.</hi> 13.41. and the dead, <hi>viz.</hi> the before ſuffering Saints until then, <hi>viz.</hi> with a judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of reward, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.18, 19. and 22.12. who ſhall upon their raiſing then with their ſpiritual Bodies, enjoy all the covenanted Mercies in that ſaid ſtate with Chriſt 1000 years: and the iike judging of the quick again, <hi>viz.</hi> of the laſt Gog and Magog, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.9. and of the dead then, <hi>viz.</hi> of the wicked to be raiſed at the laſt Trump, will be upon the Saints general momentany change and rapture, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. to receive the final ſentence of them both, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. That the Reſurrection of the juſt, or firſt ſaid Reſurrection, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.5. will be at Chriſts ſecond coming or appearance in the Clouds, 1000 years before the ſaid Reſurrection of the wicked, which he teacheth expreſly, <hi>v.</hi> 5. ſaying, The reſt of the dead lived not again (bodily as the Sants did 1000 years before) until thoſe 1000 years were finiſhed.</p>
            <p n="3">3. That ſuch a great and excellent part of that holy Communion of the Saints ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed (upon many Scriptural accounts) for the ſaid time and ſtate: when the Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions of them that are ſaved, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.24. ſuitable to <hi>Eſa.</hi> 60.3. ſhall walk in the light of the New <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> then come down [with Chriſt] from God out of Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, to be then the Bride, the Lambs Wife, <hi>v.</hi> 9, 10. See Saints Reſur. and 6 Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſions, pag. 17, 18. of <hi>Reſtitut.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">III. Thereby alſo the chiefeſt and higheſt ſcope of the three firſt Petitions of our Lords moſt divine and comprehenſive Prayer is both made known, and to be eminent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly attainable, <hi>viz.</hi> in that World to come, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.5. both which follow from the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Aſſertions: And this is grounded upon the ſame Scripture foundations for our Faith to reſt upon, <hi>Viz.</hi>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Hallowed be thy Name</item>
                  <item>2. Thy Kingdom come</item>
                  <item>3. Thy Will be done</item>
               </list> and all three will be in Earth (then) as it is (now) in Heaven.</p>
            <p>As alſo [This Day] ſeems to be annexed to the other three Petitions, to teach us they ought to be daily ſought for by Prayer to God.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Viz.</hi> 
               <list>
                  <item>1. This Days Bread.</item>
                  <item>2. This Days pardon of ſin, with our pardoning others.</item>
                  <item>3. This Days preſervation or deliverance from the Evil one, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>All which will moſt largely be granted in that time and ſtate, as the holy Scriptures alſo teach, as in <hi>Irenic. &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That theſe very excellent benefits are warranted from the moſt Divine Authority of Jeſus Chriſt himſelf, is moſt apparent by the right underſtanding of our Divine Scheme, and very apt Revelation Key, and by our whole work.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:102127:2"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="scheme">
            <pb facs="tcp:102127:11"/>
            <head>The Scheme of Gods Eternal Great Deſigne in the World for Chriſt and his Elect Saints, given to him by the Father upon the Performance of his Great Work of Mediatorſhip, as is manifeſt from his Word in theſe Four Great Things enſuing: which are all by our Saviours <hi>Revelation Key</hi> Applyed to the Seventh <hi>Millennium.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>1. By his Eternal appointing of Chriſt to be Heir of all things at the end of 6000. Years, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.2. and <hi>Heb.</hi> 3 &amp; 4 <hi>ch.</hi> when the Saints ſhall be Heirs, and Joynt-heirs with him, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.7. <hi>Rom,</hi> 8.17, 18, 19, 20.</item>
               <item>2. By making an Eternal Covenant with Chriſt, to give the Elect to him upon his fulfilling of his great work of Redemption of Men &amp; Creatures, as <hi>Iſa.</hi> 62.6. &amp; <hi>Iſa.</hi> 59. <hi>ult.</hi> to be in that time and ſtate his Bride the Lambs Wife, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.2, 9.</item>
               <item>3. By his Declared Purpoſe to Create the World for Chriſt and his ſaid Saints to Inherit then, when he will put all things under his Feet, and make all things New for him and them, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.5, 7. this Decree proved from <hi>Pſ.</hi> 8.4. expounded by <hi>Heb.</hi> 2. <hi>v.</hi> 6, 7, 8.</item>
               <item>4. By his declared Decree that after all oppoſition in the ſaid 6000 years Enmity notwithſtanding; yet, ſaith he, then, in the Seventh <hi>Millennium,</hi> I will ſet my King [Chriſt] upon my Holy Hill of <hi>Sion,</hi> and his Saints ſhall Reign with him, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.4, 6.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="2">2. God by Chriſt Created the World in ſix dayes, in a ſtate fit to carry on his ſaid Eternal Deſignes in the ſaid four Par<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>iculars, and Reſted the ſeventh day, as foreſeeing <hi>Adams</hi> Fall (if he upheld him not in that ſtate by his own Almighty Arme, which he was not pleaſed then to do, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as in our Divine Theſes, 1, 2, 3, 4, &amp;c. in our <hi>Irenic.</hi>) And to Type out Chriſts work of Redemption in 6000 years before the great Sabbatiſme of Reſt be obtained for himſelf and his ſaid Bride the Lambs Wife in the ſeventh, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.2, 9.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Upon the Fall of Man in reference to his ſaid Eternal Deſigns he makes his General Declaration of his purpoſed Grace by Chriſt, the Promiſed Seed of the Woman, and being only of the Woman, (implyed he ſhould alſo be the Son of God:) and then likewiſe put Enmity between the Serpent and the Woman, and his Seed and her Seed, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3 15. which ſaid Promiſed Seed ſhould in due time be manifeſt indeed to be the Son of God, Mighty to Save; who ſhould both break the Serpents Head of Policie, and Power, in the ſaid 6000 years, and then obtain the loſt Dominion of the World and Creatures by Mans Fall, for himſelf and his ſaid Saints or Spiritual Seed at the end thereof, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.6, 7. <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.5, 8. <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.5.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Chriſt upon the ſaid Declared Grace of the Father, through himſelf undertakes (as the Goel or Redeemer) to carry on that work in 6000 years, until his Sabbatiſme of Reſt for himſelf and his Saints then ſhould come, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.7. <hi>Hebrews</hi> 4.9.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>[N. B.]</hi> This moſt comprehenſive Divinity, being grounded upon Holy Scripture, muſt needs be the beſt Divinity: 1. As being ſuitable to Gods ſaid Decrees. 2. Revealed and Promiſed to the Fathers, 3. Confirmed and Explained by all the Holy Prophets. 4. Witneſſed to by Chriſt in the Goſpels, and the Apoſtles in all their Writings. 5. Divinely Unlocked by Chriſts <hi>Revelation;</hi> and all this Taught all along in the ſaid 6000 Years by the ſame Glorious Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of the Infinitely Wiſe God; and ſo far alſo now carryed on by Chriſt almoſt to the Seventh <hi>Millennium:</hi> Therefore, Let all ſorts of Perſons, without a Divine Warrant, beware of Cutting Chriſts ſaid Work of Redemption ſhorter than Gods Word hath made it, and doth declare it to be, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> (But more of ſome of theſe afterwards.)</p>
            <p n="1">
               <pb facs="tcp:102127:12"/>1. That theſe ſaid times of Gods ſaid Eternal Deſignes to be carryed on by Chriſt, are manifeſt by his Word to be done in 6000 Years, in reference to his own, and his Saints Injoyments in the Seventh, which may fitly be called Gods and Chriſts Divine <hi>Millenniariſme.</hi> And this may be Manifeſt,
<list>
                  <item>1. From the Explication of the Lord the Spirit in his own ſacred Word, who doth himſelf make ſuch a reſemblance of the times of Chriſts ſaid Redemption, to the dayes of the Worlds Creation, <hi>Heb.</hi> 3, &amp; 4, <hi>ch.</hi> and of the Typical Reſt in <hi>Canaan</hi> under <hi>Joſhua</hi>'s conduct to Chriſts ſaid Divine Reſt: of which ſee <hi>pag.</hi> 3. of <hi>Introduct.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2. The holy Scripture as the ground of that Reſemblance, Teſtified by <hi>Moſes,</hi> Pſal. 90.4. That 10 0 years with God or Chriſt was but as yeſterday, in the Old Teſtament; and St. <hi>Peter</hi> in the New, urgeth it as a great point to be known by all Chriſtians, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3.8. And Chriſt very exactly determines the ſaid Sabbatiſm ſuitable to ſuch other dayes to be 1000 years, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20. ſix times over, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſee much more, <hi>p.</hi> 3, 4, &amp;c.</item>
                  <item>3. By Gods frequent expreſſion of Mercy to be ſhewed to 1000 Generations, which appears to be meant in the 7000 years of the Worlds continuance, as three Lives are reckoned to be 21 years, taking in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſed Mercies of the ſeventh as in our Key is explained, in reſpect of the middle <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, or ſtate of things, <hi>pag.</hi> 3.</item>
                  <item>4. By <hi>Moſes</hi> his Chronology revealed for times paſt 2400 years or more, and until <hi>Solomons</hi> Temple built 3000, and at the Captivity of <hi>Babylon,</hi> ſaith Biſhop <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher,</hi> 3450 years; then <hi>Daniels</hi> great Calender of 2300 years until Chriſts 1000 years, make up in all 6750 years to the little ſpace of Satan looſed. Alſo that apt Computation of <hi>Bucolcerus</hi> to like purpoſe, <hi>page</hi> 3.</item>
                  <item>5. From Chriſt firſt Revealed, <hi>Gen</hi> 3.15. to be neceſſarily in the fulneſs of time God manifeſt in the Fleſh in 4000 years, (as ſaith Biſhop <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher</hi>) and his Seſſion, and Interceſſion in Heaven until the end of the ſixth <hi>Millen.</hi> and his glorious Reign on Earth 1000 years, which makes up the ſame Account 'till Satans looſing, <hi>&amp;c. page</hi> 3.</item>
                  <item>6. From the Reſemblances of <hi>Davids</hi> and <hi>Solomons</hi> Kingdome and Temple about 3000 years Typifying Chriſts Kingdome, and himſelf the Antitype in all reſpects at 6000 years, when the Lord God Almighty and the Lamb will be the Temple of the City, for twice ſo long continuance as their Kingdomes or the Temple remained before in the World. Alſo their Tribe and People being carried Captive for ſin, about the middle of 7000 years of the worlds continuance points out the different ſtate of them; when God, according to his Covenant, ſhall take away their ſin, <hi>Rom.</hi> 11. when the Devil, and the worlds laſt Gog and Magog ſhall not reach them, but themſelves ſhall periſh by that attempt, <hi>ch.</hi> 20. 8, 9. <hi>page</hi> 4.</item>
                  <item>7. In the Golden Rings of all Sabbath Circulations: The ſeventh <hi>Millenium</hi> is the Diamond, <hi>viz.</hi> of Annual, Monethly and Daily Sabbaths, (which laſt and longeſt) chiefly points it out, as <hi>Heb.</hi> 3 &amp; 4. but the Jubelie after the ſeven times ſeven ſeems to relate to Eternity, after the ſeventh <hi>Millennium</hi> ſhall be compleated.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>And whereas it may be Objected, that the ſixth</hi> Millennium <hi>will ſo want above</hi> 200 <hi>years.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> 1. Chriſt ſpeaks of ſhortning evil times for the Elects ſake; he may ſpecially mean it of that time.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The firſt Ages may be in ſome part unknown to Men, though <hi>Moſes</hi> ſet down the Ages of the firſt Fathers, he doth not aſſert that to be a perfect Chronicle; and for <hi>Cainans</hi> age there is difficulty, <hi>Luke</hi> 3. which is not mentioned <hi>Mat.</hi> 3. nor <hi>Gen.</hi> 10.24. Alſo the end of the world is ſet forth by an indeffinite little ſpace of Satan looſed; but ſince the Spirit of God reſembles the firſt 6000 years to the ſix dayes of the Creation, he knows how to make up the Account, though Men cannot: and Chriſt hath ſtrongly aſſerted the Sabbatiſme of 1000 years, which is ſuitable to the ſix before it, <hi>page</hi> 3.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The ſhortneſs of the ſixth <hi>Millen.</hi> may ſeem ſo to be more ſuitable to the ſixth day; in the end whereof Satan ſeduced <hi>Eve,</hi> and ſhe her Husband: God in the cool of the day Summons, Arraigns, and Senten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceth all the three Offenders, and caſts <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eve</hi> out of <hi>Paradiſe</hi> (as is moſt probable) (which would require ſome conſiderable time.) [ſee more to this purpoſe in <hi>p</hi> 4, &amp;c.] and we know not but the little ſaid ſpace being a like evil time, may be allotted to make up the 6000 year, <hi>page</hi> 3.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Of all conſiderable Computations of Times in Holy Scripture, I find none ſo exact and certain as that 2300 years, <hi>Daniel</hi> 8, given by <hi>Palmoni</hi> the ſecret Numberer. [See our many Reaſons for it in our Summary on <hi>Daniel</hi> upon that ſaid Number:] which is the complete meaſure of the four Gentile Monarchies and Jews Bondage (now both almoſt expired) from the Captivity of <hi>Babylon</hi> to Chriſts appearance; by which both <hi>Daniels</hi> other Numbers are meaſured.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That of his 70 Weeks, or 490 Years from the twentieth year of <hi>Artaxerxes Longimanus, Anno Mundi</hi> 3550<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> reaching to the end of the halfe Week, after Chriſt by his D ath had finiſhed Tranſgreſſion; and by his Reſurrection had brought in everlaſting Righteouſneſs, <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.24. at his Aſcention beginning the Kingdome of the Stone, <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.44. for its 1666 years to break the Iron <hi>Roman</hi> Kingdome, with the remaining parts of all the former at laſt, and it ſelf become a Mountain filling the whole Earth, <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.35, 45. And alſo it is the meaſure of his laſt Number, <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.12 or 13 5 years after Sacrifice ſhould ultimately be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken away, many hundred years after that mark was given, which fell out about <hi>Anno Domini</hi> 365. in <hi>Julian</hi> the Apoſtate Emperours time; to which 1335 years being added, reach to the bleſſed times he ſpeaks of, in all which the Divine exactneſs of <hi>Daniel</hi> and <hi>Revelation</hi> in connexion one with another is very admirable.</p>
            <p>Fot the carrying on of which ſaid Deſign in the time of Chriſts Mediatorſhip, and to make good his own right, he doth 4 things
<list>
                  <item>1. He makes the <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, or ſeveral States or Providential Diſpoſals of things; 1. In the Old World. 2. In this preſent evil World from the Flood. 3. In the world to come in the 1000 years of Chriſts Reign, <hi>p</hi> 4.</item>
                  <item>2. He upholds all things by the Word of his Power, for thoſe ſaid <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, or Worlds continuance ſuitable to what he will accompliſh in them; and when the laſt ſtate is fulfilled, he will diſſolve the Created World, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.11. <hi>page</hi> 4.</item>
                  <item>3. He Purges the Sins of his ſaid Elect Saints through all the ſaid States; 1. By his Word or Revealed Will. 2. By his Blood to be ſhed, or actually ſhed. 3. By his Spirit making both the other effectual by all his own Means or Ordinances, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1.3. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 59. <hi>ult.</hi> page 4.</item>
                  <item>4. He carries on his work of Redemption in the firſt 6000 years, as the work the Father gave him to do therein; namely, in the Execution of his three great Offices, of the great Prophet, Prieſt, and King, for the good of his Univerſal true Church in the three great Periods of the World. The <hi>Firſt,</hi> Under the Old Teſtament, in 4000 years. The <hi>Second,</hi> Under the New, in the next 2000 years. And the <hi>Third,</hi> In the World to come, in the laſt thouſand years: as largely proved in our Treat. on <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>I. <hi>Millennium.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>II. <hi>Millen.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>III. <hi>Millen.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>IV. <hi>Millen.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>V. <hi>Millen.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>VI. <hi>Millen.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>VII. <hi>Millen.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>This his Work of Redemption hath two Parts; 1. By removing of Evil, or breaking the Serpents Head. 2. By procuring all Promiſed Good. The firſt he doth,
<list>
                  <item>1. By his breaking the Serpents head both of Power and Policy. 1. Of his Power, which is to be done in his great day of Judgment; which was firſt more generlly Revealed to <hi>Enoch,</hi> Jude 13.14. in the Old World. 2. By the firſt act of his Judgment, when his Foes ſhall be made his footſtool, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 110.1. which was more eſpecially ſeen by <hi>Daniel</hi> in Viſion in the New World, <hi>ch.</hi> 7. when he will do it eminently at the Beaſts Deſtruction: The laſt act is revealed only by Chriſt, to be the total breaking of it, after the 1000 years.</item>
                  <item>2. By deſtroying his works of Policy by all his wicked Inſtruments, more generally or more particularly; as firſt, for their height of ſin, then drowning the Old World, and then ſaved <hi>Noah</hi> and his Family; and after bringing all Satans three <hi>Babels</hi> to confuſion in the ſeveral times of the New World, affording ſucceſſively helps againſt the miſchief of them, as in <hi>Irenic.</hi> c. 5. and laſtly reſtoring the good by him impaired thereby at the end of 6000 years; <hi>viz.</hi> for Confuſion of Tongues, Oneneſs of Speech: for oppreſſive Tyranny, good and peaceable Government: for Myſtical <hi>Babylons</hi> Deluſions, pure and untainted Truth.</item>
                  <item>3. By more ordinary, and particular diſappointments of his Deſignes by his Angels, Servants, Creatures ordinarily, beſides what he doth extraordinarily more publickly or privately in the 6000 years, which he is doing in all that time of the 6000 years of actual Enmity betwixt the Seed of the Serpent, and the Seed of the Woman, in one place or other, or many; in one time, manner, means or other, as ſeems beſt unto him.</item>
                  <item>4. By ſhewing himſelf as Lord of Hoſts, and the grand Captain of his <hi>Iſrael,</hi> as <hi>Joſh.</hi> 5. through all the ſaid Spiritual Warfare to mannage his own Hoſts (yea and his Enemies too, as oft as he pleaſeth) a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Hoſts and Legions of the Enemies, Men or Devils, or inferiour Creatures; and at the end of the 6000 years, defeating, deſtroying, or impriſoning all his Churches greateſt Enemies; <hi>viz. Ezekiels</hi> Gog and Magog, with other leſſer Enemies; and binding Satan for 1000 years, and giving reſt to his Saints at that his appearance, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.7. and Kingdome, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1.</item>
                  <item>5. By his Triumphant and Victorious laughing them all to Scorne, (as oft, and by what contemptible means he pleaſeth) of which variety man is not able to recount or conceive, ſo mighty is he to break them all in the ſaid time.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. He Redeemeth by procuring, and carrying on all Promiſed Good;</p>
            <p n="1">1. Through Chriſt all following Promiſes of Good by Covenants made with the Fathers after the firſt ſaid General one, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15. are procured by him, and the good of them carried on for them and their ſaid Spiritual Seed in the ſame 6000 years to be enjoyed in the ſeventh.</p>
            <p n="1">1. To <hi>Noah,</hi> in re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpect of whom three things are obſervable in the 2d. <hi>Millen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. In that by his Type of the Ark he ſaved his own Houſe, foreſhewing how Chriſt will be the ſafe Arke of his true Church from the Fires of Wrath on the Wicked at the beginning and end of the 1000 years, <hi>page</hi> 8.</p>
            <p n="2">2. God made with him a Covenant, confirmed by the Rainbow, <hi>Gen.</hi> 8. to preſerve Man and Beaſt, and to Accommodate both, by ſufficient Fruitfulneſs all the 6000 years, ordinarily; and promiſed after the greateſt Fruitfulneſs in the ſeventh <hi>Millenium, page</hi> 8</p>
            <p n="3">3. Then alſo God by his Propheſie, <hi>Gen.</hi> 9. ſhewed that the Elect till Chriſts ſecond comeing ſhould (moſtly) deſcend from his two Sons, <hi>Shem</hi> and <hi>Japhet; viz.</hi> Jews and Gentiles in their times; yet others (haply) Proſelites: Firſt then <hi>Shems</hi> Race, the Jews, had the then preſent Mercie, until they had killed the Lord of Life, But then <hi>Japhets</hi> Race were perſwaded to dwell in the Tents of <hi>Shem,</hi> (as <hi>Acts</hi> 13.) <hi>viz</hi> to be of the True Church of G d; and both of them will be ſo together in the 1000 years; as was foretold in that Song for Poſterity, <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.43. and is applyed by the Apoſtle, <hi>Rom.</hi> 15. <hi>page</hi> 8.</p>
            <p>Alſo in the Second <hi>Millennium</hi> God made Covenants with <hi>Abraham, Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Jacob.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. With <hi>Abraham</hi> in ſeven Gradations, as <hi>page</hi> 7, 8, 9. of our <hi>Key:</hi> firſt that in him and his Seed all Nations ſhould be bleſſed; namely, in that his own Divine Seed Chriſt, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3 through whom the bleſſing of <hi>Abraham</hi> came upon the Gentiles, (as ſaith the Apoſtle) after the Jews were caſt off, and will come again upon both joyntly, at the end of 6000 years, and throughout the ſeventh <hi>Millennium.</hi> Alſo unto <hi>Abraham</hi> and his Seed, <hi>Canaan,</hi> with the Holy City in its time was promiſed; but for him, <hi>Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> the chief intent was in the Renewed State thereof, in which ſence the Apoſtle ſaith, he was Heir of the World by Faith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4.13. which he with his Spiritual Seed ſhall then have; [even that Great, Holy, and Beloved <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> comeing (then) down from God out of Heaven, having Foundations whoſe Maker and Builder is God, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.10, 16, 40.] after 6000 years: But the Typical <hi>Canaan</hi> Conditionally given to his Naturrl Race, was to them a polluted Reſt by their Sin; and therefore it caſt them out with a ſore Deſtruction, <hi>Mic.</hi> 2.10.</p>
            <p n="2">2. To <hi>Iſaac</hi> the like Covenants were renewed for the ſame, to him and his Spiritual Seed, which will be alſo made good at the end of the ſixth <hi>Millennium,</hi> and throughout all the ſeventh, <hi>pag.</hi> 9, of our <hi>Key, page</hi> 9. of <hi>Introduct.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. To <hi>Jacob</hi> and his Spiritual Seed the like was again ratified: whence God is the God of <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob,</hi> through all Generations; which is his Memorial until all their Covenants be compleated to the end of the ſeventh <hi>Millennium,</hi> page 9. of our <hi>Key.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the 3d <hi>Millen.</hi> God made his Covenant with <hi>David</hi> for his ſure Mercies reſpecting Chriſts Kingdome in the 1000 years af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter his Natural Race's long Bondage for Sin.</p>
            <p>Yet firſt <hi>David</hi> and his Natural Race enjoyed the Typical <hi>Canaan,</hi> and their <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> about 450 years, until that by their increaſed Provocations there was no remedy, but they muſt go Captive to <hi>Babylon,</hi> as the Ten Tribes of <hi>Iſrael</hi> went many years before into <hi>Aſſyria:</hi> Both which Captivities were to continue, as God then Revealed by <hi>Daniel,</hi> ch. 8. all the 2300 years of the four Mettle Kingdoms, <hi>ch.</hi> 2. at the end whereof the Spiritual Seed of <hi>David</hi> with himſelf (through that his one Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Seed Chriſt) ſhall poſſeſs <hi>Davids</hi> Kingdome, with the Holy City which <hi>Ahraham</hi> looked for, and both in the Renewed ſtate of them; and though <hi>Davids</hi> Taber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nacle fell at <hi>Babylons</hi> Captivity, yet then it ſhall be rai ed again, <hi>Amos</hi> 9. at Chriſts appearance and Kingdome, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1. <hi>Acts</hi> 15.16. <hi>pag.</hi> 9, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of our <hi>Key.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Moreover, God was pleaſed to ſhew Mercy to <hi>Davids</hi> People, after 70 years to reduce them by <hi>Cyrus,</hi> to fulfil in due time, <hi>Jacobs</hi> Propheſie of the come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of <hi>Shilo, Gen.</hi> 49. by ſending (then) the great Meſſiah, towards the end of <hi>Daniels</hi> 70 Weeks, or 490 Years, by his firſt comeing in Humility to ſuffer and perform all Gods Wills, putting an end to Tranſgreſſion by his Death, and bringing in everlaſting Righteouſneſs by his Reſurrection; and forty dayes after by his Aſcention to improve that his great Work of Reconciliation by his Death, and by his Interceſſion ever ſince, at Gods right hand on his Fathers Throne, during Gods Kingdome of the Stone for its 1666 years, Divinely in that time deſtroying the laſt <hi>Roman</hi> Iron Kingdome, with the Remainders of the former, <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.35. when he comes from thence to ſit on his own Throne, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.21. <hi>page</hi> 9.</p>
            <p>This Sovereign Antidote againſt Atheiſme, Profaneneſs, and all Errour contrary hereunto; and alſo as an excellent means to promote all contrary good (if God ſhall ſet it home) is conſcienciouſly to be applyed by all Chriſtians for themſelves and others: for which purpoſe let us all Pray that God would give his bleſſing and good ſucceſs thereunto. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="explanation">
               <pb facs="tcp:102127:13" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <head>The Compoſer of the Divine Scheme (explained by that very apt decypher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Chriſts moſt precious Key of the ſame Divine Grace) earneſtly ſeeking the good and ſatisfaction of all men, by ſuch now ſeaſonable great and gracious Diſcoveries thereby evidently manifeſt, (that all ſuch branches as are not really tranſplanted into the true Vine, may earneſtly and ſpeedily labour to get into that eſtate; and ſuch as are tranſplanted already may bring forth their due fruit therein, and that he may the better ſet home all other Scriptural Conſiderations, doth now thereunto farther add many Convincing Evidences (than what he ſet down <hi>Aſſert. 7.</hi> of his <hi>Key,</hi> and in many other parts formerly) of theſe two things; <hi>viz. 1.</hi> Of the Perſonality of Chriſts appearance and Reign at the beginning of his great day of Judgment. <hi>2.</hi> Of the now neer approach thereof; which he purpoſeth (if God will) to annex as an Appendix thereunto: The Summarie of both here follows.</head>
               <p>AS to the firſt, their Perſonality is ſtrongly proved ſo by many heads of Arguments drawn from the drift of the whole Divine Scheme, carrying on Gods Deſign of Chriſts Mediatory Kingdom in the Iſhue, as God-man, and the Son of <hi>David:</hi> And 2. In the four particulars explained by Chriſts <hi>Revelation</hi> reſpecting that happy time and ſtate: And 3. from the particular Covenants and Promiſes gradually carrying on the ſame, being alſo explained by the Prophets, Goſpels, Apoſtles Writings; and eſpecially by the <hi>Revelation,</hi> ſhewing the true meaning of all the other.</p>
               <p n="4">4. By many apt and evident expreſſions and proofs in the Old and New Teſtament of his ſaid perſonal appearance and Kingdom.</p>
               <p n="5">5. From many Divine Evidences that the great day of Judgment (or <hi>Matutinum Judicium</hi> thereof) then begins; as Jewiſh Rabbies alſo underſtood that firſt Seſſion of the Judgment at the Beaſts Ruine, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7. which is farther proved by all the four marks of the day of Judgment, and by both parts thereof, in judging the quick and dead, bad and good; the laſt with rewards, whoſe lot fell out to be under the ſuffering times and ſtate of the Church both of Jews and Gentiles, and of all Saints until Chriſts ſecond comeing: [the like marks and parts will be of the <hi>Veſper. Judicium,</hi> ſet forth by by Chriſt <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.11, &amp;c.]</p>
               <p n="6">6. From the many great things then peculiarly to be done by Chriſt and none elſe: As 1. To bring all the ſaid Saints with him, <hi>Zach.</hi> 14.5. 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 3. <hi>ult.</hi> 2. From his raiſing (then) their ſpiritual Bodies. 3. From his commanding his Enemies then to be brought and ſlain be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him. <hi>Luke</hi> 19. 4. From his being ſeen then with the eyes of Jews and Gentiles through the Clouds, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.7. 5. From his feet's ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing on Mount <hi>Olivet, Zach.</hi> 14. Upon his deſcending (then probably) to convert the Jews, by means of his wonderful cleaving that moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, ſhakings of the Earth, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 2.19, 21. and deſtruction of the ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies then, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 39.8. with his eminent pouring his Spirit upon them, <hi>Joel</hi> 2. <hi>Zach.</hi> 12.10.</p>
               <p n="7">7. His receiving then his Univerſal and perpetual Kingdom, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.13, 14, 27.</p>
               <p n="8">8. His ſitting on the Throne of his Father <hi>David, Luke</hi> 1.32. In all which and the like actings, he muſt neceſſarily then be perſonally preſent. And</p>
               <p n="9">9. In his whole Reign, by his executing Righteouſneſs and Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment in the Earth.</p>
               <p>The laſt Head of Arguments is from the many Relations he will then ſtand in to them: 1. As their then viſibly glorious Head, and they his viſible Members. 2. As their Divine Bridegroom, and the ſaid Saints his viſible Bride. 3. He the Husband to dwell with them, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21. and they the Lambs Wife, <hi>verſ</hi> 9. 4 He as the Heir of all things, and they joynt-heirs with him, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.7. as the Wife's Dow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. 5. As the Kingdoms of the world become then actually his, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.15. ſo they ſhall then Reign with him perſonally, <hi>chap.</hi> 20.4, 6. 6. He as the great God brings his rewards with him at his glorious appearance, <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.12. They as the perſons then brought to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warded, which by their Reſurrection become capable to receive all the happineſs promiſed in that glorious ſtate.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Why he believeth the times thereof will be about 20 years hence from <hi>An.</hi> 76. or by loſs of 4 years 80 in a latitude. 1. Becauſe all Propheſie until that time and ſtate appears to be almoſt fulfilled. 1. <hi>Daniels</hi> great Calender of the Jews Captivity, and the Gentile four Monarchies of 2300 years will about that time be expired. 2. The three Overturnings of <hi>Davids</hi> Kingdom until Chriſts be given to him, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 21.26, 27. appears almoſt fulfilled. 3. The 600 years from the fourth of <hi>Jehojakim</hi> begun, &amp; firſt of <hi>Nebuchadnezzar</hi> to Chriſts Birth at 4000, and from thence 1700 years of <hi>Revelation Propheſie</hi> to Chriſts ſecond comeing (as the two integral parts thereof) clearly make up the 2300 years; both which are many wayes proved. 4. Both <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niels</hi> other Numbers of the 70 weeks, <hi>Dan.</hi> 9. and the taking away Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, <hi>ch.</hi> 12.12. when from 365 of Chriſt, <hi>Daniels</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>335 ſhould reach to the ſaid bleſſed times and ſtate of the Jews, both which (in connexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with <hi>Revelation</hi> Numbers) end at the ſame period of Chriſts ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance, with the ſaid 2300 years, <hi>Dan.</hi> 8.</p>
               <p n="5">5. The Jews ſeeking their Land 45 years before from 1290. <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.11. to the ſaid 1335 of the bleſſed times, of which a book was formerly remarkably written, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="6">6. From the Beaſts treading the true Church under foot 42 months, with the Witneſſes, &amp; the ſaid Womans Wilderneſs ſtate, all almoſt out.</p>
               <p n="7">7. From the <hi>Turks</hi> 396 years, <hi>Rev</hi> 9.11, &amp;c. from about 1300 to end with the Beaſts laſt Ruine, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 39.8. at Chriſts appearance, <hi>Dan.</hi> 11.45. &amp; 12.1, 2.</p>
               <p n="8">8. From the probable proceedings of the Vials under the ſixth Trumpet to the ſixth Vial, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> in the end of the which will be the <hi>Armageddon</hi> Battle, and Beaſts Ruine, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.11, &amp;c.</p>
               <p n="9">9. Fr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>m the Table of the bad times, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.1. to 15. 1. As ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plicab<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e to the Saints ſufferings under the four firſt Seals, and the Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ine of the <hi>Roman</hi> Civil State thereupon, by the blaſts of the ſix firſt Trumpets. 2. As applicable to the Eccleſiaſtical ſtate, both as to the Regular times meaſured, <hi>v.</hi> 1. and the Beaſts 42 months caſt out, which the Vials under the ſixth Trumpet conſume by degrees, until his laſt Ruine at Chriſts ſecond comeing, ſoon after the burning of the Whore of <hi>Babylon</hi> (as appears from <hi>Rev.</hi> 18, &amp; 19, <hi>ch.</hi>) beſides ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny other ſignes of theſe laſt times, more ordinarily now obſervable in ſundry particulars, to be expreſſed in the ſaid Appendix; As Iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty abounding, Charity co<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d, St. <hi>Peters</hi> Atheiſtical Scoffers at Religion, open Prophaneſs, and the unclean Spirits Prevalency ſo to carry on his two-fold Antichriſtianiſm, formerly in Doctrinals, <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, in the latt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r times, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> more lately in Formalities; <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>, in the laſt dayes, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.1. to <hi>verſ.</hi> 10.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="key">
               <pb facs="tcp:102127:14"/>
               <p>CHRIST'S Divine <hi>Revelation Key</hi> in the four laſt Chapters may aptly be Decyphered in theſe four Reſpects; <hi>Viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">1. In the Handle of it, ſetting forth his Mercy [then] to <hi>Jews</hi> &amp; <hi>Gentiles</hi> at his 2d Comeing; for, ſaith the Spirit,</p>
               <p>Behold he Cometh with Clouds, and every Eye ſhall ſee him, and they alſo which Pierced him; and all Kindreds of the Earth ſhall Wail becauſe of him; Even ſo, Amen. <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.7.</p>
               <p>The Seven <hi>Aſian</hi> Churches have their ſeveral Promiſes to be Fulfilled to every Overcomer at the firſt Reſurrection:
<list>
                     <item>1. For <hi>Epheſus,</hi> to Eat of the Tree of Life in the midd'ſt of the Paradiſe of God, <hi>Chap.</hi> 2. <hi>verſ.</hi> 5.</item>
                     <item>2. <hi>Smyrna,</hi> for ſhe ſhall not be hurt of the Second Death, <hi>v.</hi> 11.</item>
                     <item>3. <hi>
                           <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ergamus</hi> ſhall Eat of the hidden Manna, <hi>verſ.</hi> 17.</item>
                     <item>4. <hi>Thyatira</hi> ſhall have Power over the Nations, <hi>v.</hi> 26. and give him the Morning-ſtar, <hi>verſe</hi> 28.</item>
                     <item>5. <hi>Sardis</hi> ſhall be cloathed in white, &amp; I will confeſs his name before my Father, <hi>c.</hi> 3. 5.</item>
                     <item>6. <hi>Philadelphia,</hi> I will make him a Piller in the Houſe of God, and he ſhall have a new Name, <hi>v.</hi> 12</item>
                     <item>7. <hi>Laodicea,</hi> ſhall ſit with Chriſt on his Throne, <hi>v.</hi> 21.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p n="2">2. The long Stail thereof paſſeth through 1700. Years of Suffering Times, by Promiſes and Encouragements, to <hi>ch.</hi> 20.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In the Seal-Propheſie,</hi> ch 6.</p>
               <p n="1">1. The 144000 Sealed in the Eaſt, <hi>ch.</hi> 7. and innume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable others, all to he rewar<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded in the 1000 years, <hi>v.</hi> 15, 16, 17.</p>
               <p n="2">2. Thoſe killed under the Dragon, until 320 years en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, with their Brethren &amp; fellow Servants after to be killed under the Beaſt in his 42 Moneths until the ſaid 1000 years; but both to be rewarded together at the firſt Reſurrection, <hi>Reſur. p.</hi> 36. <hi>c.</hi> 20. <hi>v.</hi> 4, 6.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>In the Book-Propheſie,</hi> ch. 10.</p>
               <p n="1">1. Quickly after the Riſing and Aſcending of the two laſt finiſhing Witneſſes, the 7th Angel ſounds, when the Kingdoms of the World be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come Chriſts actually, <hi>Rev</hi> 11.15.</p>
               <p n="2">2. In the time of the Vials <hi>ch.</hi> 15. the Victors over the Beaſt ſtand on a Sea of Glaſs &amp; ſing the Song of <hi>Moſes</hi> in Triumph over their Enemies <hi>v.</hi> 2, 3. and all ſuch Over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comers ſhall rejoyce at the Whores Deſolation, <hi>c.</hi> 18.20. All ſorts of Saints ſhall then ſing aloud their many Hale<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lujah's, &amp; ſhall ſoon after the ruine of the Beaſt, <hi>c.</hi> 19.1, 2, 3, 4, &amp; <hi>v.</hi> 11, 20. Reign with Chriſt, <hi>ch.</hi> 20.4. at the end of 1700 Years. See <hi>Arg.</hi> 7.</p>
               <p n="3">3. The Subſtance of the ſame Key in 8 Particulars, wherein Predictions &amp; Revelations fitly ſuit each to other.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>1. Judgment againſt Ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies.</item>
                  <item>2. A Paradiſe for Saints.</item>
                  <item>3. Fruitfulneſs proper to that time.</item>
                  <item>4. Lines of Holy Seed, or the <hi>New Jeruſalem</hi> State.</item>
                  <item>5. Nations ſaved walk in her Light.</item>
                  <item>6. New Heavens &amp; New Earth for both.</item>
                  <item>7. Chriſts Kingdom for both of them in their own ſtates.</item>
                  <item>8. The firſt are raiſed for it; the ſecond obtain by Promiſe.</item>
               </list>
               <p>Such Mercies Couched before in Gods Word, Chriſt hath thus Divinely diſplayed. See the Picture of our Key, <hi>page</hi> 63. of <hi>Reſur.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Behold, I come quickly, <hi>&amp;c. v.</hi> 22</p>
               <p>Surely I come quickly, even ſo come L. Jeſus, c. 22. 20.</p>
               <p>Behold, I come quickly, <hi>&amp;c. v.</hi> 12</p>
               <p n="4">4. The Curious Work in the ſaid Key, may be ſeen in theſe 3 things; <hi>viz.</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. The Spirit of God <hi>ch.</hi> 19. 9. ſpeaking of the Beaſts Ruine, as fore told, <hi>Daniel</hi> 7. ſaith only theſe are the true ſayings of God; but of Promiſes and Covenants, <hi>ch.</hi> 2. 5. and 22. 6. he ſaith wice, theſe Sayings are Faithful and True.</item>
                     <item>2. He marks out the time [when] by the great Voice from the Throne, ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ying, It is done <hi>ch.</hi> 20. 5. &amp; by a like Voice, ſaying, It is done <hi>chap.</hi> 16. 17. denoting the Coincidence in time, of Satans Binding, and Gods Renovation of all things; which is fully explained, <hi>p.</hi> 61, 62. of <hi>Reſtit.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3. The Time [how long] is exactly Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolved by Chriſt, to be 1000. years ſix times over, three times Abſolutely, and three times Relatively, as is Explained on ſeveral Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts, <hi>page</hi> 14. of <hi>Introduction.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
               </p>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div type="section">
            <head>The INTIMATION.</head>
            <p>Theſe Gracious Diſcoveries of untainted Divine Truths of the Goſpel being the Teſtimony of Jeſus, and the Spirit of Propheſie, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.10. are therefore the beſt Foundations of the beſt Divinity, affording the beſt Gui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance for the underſtanding of all Prophetick Scripture, both for removing of evil, as to the breaking of the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pents head, and obtaining of good, according to the promiſed Mercies and Covenants to and with the Fathers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as <hi>Introduct.</hi> p. 13, 14, 15. and in other parts; but conſequently do not afford any juſt grounds of Satans ancien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter or modern affixed Errours and Scandals, which by ſound judgment fall to the Dung-hill, like the dryed Scabs which he had maliciouſly wrought upon <hi>Jobs</hi> Body when God healed him; as <hi>Aſſer.</hi> 2, 3, 4 of our <hi>Key.</hi> And we need not marvel at Satans malice againſt theſe ſacred Doctrines, becauſe they manifeſt his long Impriſonment in the bottomleſs Pit is nigh, and that ſhortly after will follow (by his ſtrong Chain of Darkneſs) his caſting into the Fiery Lake for ever: wherefore they are indeed very uſeful, eſpecially in theſe laſt dayes, as the Spirit of Chriſt by his Word hath been (in Mercy) pleaſed ſo to open them, to be now duly improved by all men; and let all ſorts duly conſider Chriſts terrible Threat, <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.18, 19, &amp;c. Wherefore as I judged it my duty (and was prepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring) to tender them firſt to our King's Majeſty, joyntly with his Parliament, had they ſitten a week longer; ſo now I ſhall offer them (as God may afford me opportunity) to any conſiderable Companies, Aſſemblies, or Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This Intimation was preſented, ſince the Parliament, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to the KING'S Majeſty alone, with the whole Work, by an Addreſs, <hi>December 4. 1675.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let men now labour moſt earneſtly for true ſaying Fruit-bearing Faith, and ſecure it to themſelves and others, by their improving all their Lords Talents until he comes, like Wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e Virgins, with Oyl in their Veſſels, and their Lamps burning, <hi>Mat.</hi> 25. for all living perſons Talents muſt ſhortly be accounted for without exception or ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emption of any, by reaſon of their preſent diſtinguiſhing worldly Circumſtances.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:102127:3"/>
         </div>
         <div type="appendix">
            <pb facs="tcp:102127:4"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:102127:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>A brief, but weighty, Appendix to our Scheme, for the farther needful ſatisfaction of all perſons in theſe two now needful things to be conſidered.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>
                  <hi>Firſt,</hi> That Chriſts now neer-approaching Appearance and Reign will very evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently be perſonal at the deſtruction of the Beaſt, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19, &amp; 20 <hi>ch.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Secondly,</hi> We ſhall give a farther account of our many Divine Reaſons why we re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally believe that Chriſts ſaid perſonal appearance or comeing in the Clouds will be about 20 years hence in a latitude; from 76. which by the loſs of 4 years is to be reckoned 1680. as <hi>pag.</hi> 55, 56, 57. of <hi>Restitution.</hi>
               </p>
            </argument>
            <p>AS for the former, we have already briefly ſet down very much evidence thereof, both of our own former proofs thereof, and of others, in <hi>Aſſert.</hi> 7. of our <hi>Key;</hi> and in other parts, unto which we ſhall here alſo add many other weighty Conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons; [and the rather, by reaſon we find all the ſaid former proofs are ſo little hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to duly weighed by moſt men, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>] as namely theſe enſuing.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That in the drift of our whole Divine Scheme, being explained according to Chriſts <hi>Revelation,</hi> [the beſt Reſolver in the whole world] which manifeſts that the ſaid perſonal appearance and Reign of Chriſt in his Davidical Kingdom in the world are carryed on all along as the greateſt thing to be accompliſhed therein, and the drift of all the other promiſed Mercies in the 1000 years: And that firſt, as Gods eternal Deſign before all time witneſſed to in his Word in 4 things. Secondly, in time, as carryed on by Predictions, Covenants and Promiſes, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. As Gods eternal Deſign for Chriſt, and thoſe which he had given him in the world, upon his fulfilling of his great work of Redemption for them in the firſt 6000 years, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And therein firſt, as Chriſt was eternally appointed to be heir of all things, <hi>Heb.</hi> 1. in the ſeventh <hi>Millennium,</hi> ſo Chriſt aſſures the ſaid Saints that they alſo ſhall then inherit all things, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.7. or be then heirs, and joynt heirs with him alſo, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.20, 21. which requires his and their joynt perſonal preſence, together with that Inheritance, <hi>&amp;c</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. As God by an eternal Covenant had given them to him upon the fulfilling of his ſaid great work of Redemption in the 6000 years before, then to be his bride the Lambs Wife, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.9 and ſo they ſhall have then the Wife's intereſt with him in the world in all good things, together with his perſonal preſence, as we doubt not af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terwards to manifeſt, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. As God will put all things under Chriſt [in ſubjection to him] then [for we do not yet ſee it, ſaith the Apoſtle, <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.8. <hi>viz.</hi> in the preſent ſtate of things] So the Reſtitution of all things ſhall then be effected, for the perſonal enjoyment thereof both by him and them in that ſame ſtate, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.5.</p>
            <p n="4">4. As God eternally decreed to ſet his King [Chriſt] then as the Son of <hi>David</hi> God-man upon his holy Hill of <hi>Sion,</hi> wherein and whereby the excellency of all the former ſhall be compleated in the world, [notwithſtanding all the vain things which the Gentiles and Kings of the Earth have, or do, or ſhall imagin to the contrary until that time, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 2.1, 2, &amp;c.] So the ſuffering Saints ſhall then riſe and reign with him 1000 years, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.4, 6. and alſo the Heathen ſhall then be given to him for
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:102127:5"/> his Inheritance, and the uttermoſt parts of the Earth for his Poſſeſſion (as follows in that ſecond <hi>Pſalm.</hi>)</p>
            <p n="2">2. Becauſe all the promiſed Mercies and Covenants (particularly made in time (ſucceſſively) unto the Fathers, and unto their ſpiritual ſeed do refer to that ſtate of the perſonal Reign of Chriſt the ſaid 1000 years [as his own moſt Divine <hi>Revelation</hi> explains them] as to the main and principal matter or thing to be carryed on (then) for Chriſt and his ſaid Saints in that world ſhortly to come, wherein all other are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> which by the enſuing particulars (with ſundry others) may appear.</p>
            <p n="1">1. That Prediction of breaking the Serpents head [for the removing of evil] in Gods firſt and moſt comprehenſively gracious Declaration, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15. to be eminently then performed by Chriſt when comeing from the right hand of the Father, his Foes ſhall be made his footſtool, as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 110.1. according to <hi>Enochs</hi> Viſion of Chriſts great day of Judgment in the Old World; and <hi>Daniels</hi> of the ſame in the New world, to whom the time thereof was more explicitly revealed, <hi>viz.</hi> when he comes in the Clouds of Heaven, all foreſhewing the ſame time and comeing, with <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.7. foreſhown again to be executed in its order, <hi>Rev.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>9.11. when he will not only deſtroy the Beaſts but alſo the Turk with him, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 39.8. <hi>Dan.</hi> 11.45. &amp; 12 and will alſo bind Satan, and ſhut him up in the bottomleſs pit for 1000 years, taking away out of Chriſts Kingdom the evils brought into the world by ſin, <hi>viz.</hi> the Curſe, the Enmity, Bondage and Corruption, with all that offends, <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.41. at the making of the New Heavens, and the New Earth, for his Saints and Angels (then) at thoſe times of Reſtitution of all things, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.5. as is manifeſt by Scripture to be done then for Chriſt perſonally with his Saints, as in our <hi>Reſtit.</hi> largly is manifeſt; for Chriſt might as eaſily have put down Satan from being any longer the God of this preſent evil world, and Prince (by Uſurpation) of the power of the Air when he wrought his ſpiritual conqueſt over him, and all the powers of Darkneſs, <hi>Col.</hi> 2.15. at his firſt comeing, as ſoon as he had reconciled the Saints to God by the blood of his Croſs, had not the Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther moſt wiſely and holily for his own great glory, and his Sons and his ſaid Saints great glory and happineſs in that world (wherein they had ſuffered before) ſet down the order and time for the carrying on of that his great Deſign in the world for the ſaid Reign of Chriſt with his Saints, as the greateſt thing (as was ſaid) then to be ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained and enjoyed in that world to come by Chriſt and all his ſaid ſuffering Saints to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, who having before there ſuffered with him, ſhould alſo then reign with him, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.12. as he ſet forth in that book with 7 Seals given ſo gloriouſly to the Lamb, <hi>Rev.</hi> 5. to open and execute (as the Fathers Commiſſioner) in their due order and time, until about the end of 1700 years from Chriſts Birth: But that then he ſhould be his King upon his holy Hill of <hi>Sion,</hi> ſitting on the Throne of his Father <hi>David</hi> (as he had promiſed; and not until that time, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But,</p>
            <p n="2">2. The Spirit of God manifeſts that in his firſt ſaid gracious Declaration, <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15. was alſo contained the reſtoring of the Dominion over the Creatures, which includes the Kingdom of Chriſt, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20. and all that belongs to it in the two following <hi>chap.</hi> as being the poſitive end and purpoſe of Chriſts firſt undertaking of that his ſaid great work of Redemption, to be fulfilled at the time of the Reſtitution of all things; and then to be perſonally enjoyed by himſelf and his Saints, when God will wonderfully make all things new for them, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.5. when the ſuffering Saints fulneſs ſhall be then come in, and that ſame Lambs Wife hath made her ſelf ready, as <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.7. And in that ſenſe he evidently explains, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 4.6, 7. by <hi>Heb.</hi> 2.6, 7, 8. ſhewing the Son of Man there, (unto whom all things ſhall be ſurely at laſt ſubjected) to be Chriſt the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> [not the firſt <hi>Adam,</hi> who was not the Son of any man, but only the Son of God by Creation, <hi>Luke</hi> 3. <hi>ult.</hi>] and teacheth, that under the feet of
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:102127:5"/> Chriſt, the ſecond <hi>Adam,</hi> all things were to be put in ſubjection again at the ſaid time) as was by God fore-determined and appointed; though we do not yet ſee all things ſubject to him; <hi>viz.</hi> in the preſent ſtate of things, (as the Apoſtle ſpeaks, <hi>v.</hi> 8.) although for the ſuffering of Death God had before Crowned him with glory, and honour upon his becomeing lower than the Angels for a little time, whilſt he by his death had wrought reconciliation for his ſaid Saints: But as to the reſtoring of the ſaid loſt Dominion by the firſt <hi>Adams</hi> Fall, which is alſo ſtill uſurped by Satans continuing the Prince of the power of the Air, and by his wicked retinue of evil men &amp; Devils, &amp; that will not be fulfilled, until the beginning of Chriſts great day of Judgment, when all his ſaid Foes will be made his footſtool, and when the Kingdoms of the world ſhall actually become the Kingdoms of God, and of his Chriſt, and when he ſhall perſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally poſſeſs them, as being then given to him for his actual poſſeſſion of them, <hi>Pſ.</hi> 2 8.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The firſt Mercy to <hi>Shems</hi> Race the Jews, <hi>Gen.</hi> 9.26. [having then preſent in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in Gods favour] tended (as <hi>Baalam</hi> prophetically ſpake) to point out the lineage of Chriſt, who when he had reconciled his Saints by the blood of his Croſs at his firſt comeing, ſhould at his ſecond comeing be ſuch Gods King at that ſame time, whoſe Scepter was to ariſe out of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> as <hi>Numb.</hi> 24.17. which <hi>v</hi> 19. is particularly applyed to Chriſt (then) [out of <hi>Jacob</hi> (ſaid he) ſhall come he that ſhall have Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion] mainly, that in the ſaid 1000 year, carryed on after by all the Prophets, Goſpels, and all the Apoſtles Writings, and moſt Divinely ſo explained by Chriſt in the <hi>Revelation</hi> Hence alſo ſaith the Prophet <hi>Iſa. ch.</hi> 55.3. That the ſpiritual Seed of that Divine Seed of the Woman [Chriſt] ſhall with him have thoſe ſure mercies of <hi>David;</hi> that is by all the ſaid Scripture explication <hi>&amp;c.</hi> they all moſt certainly ſhall then reign with him perſonally in his ſaid Kingdom, which is the very meaning of Gods making <hi>David</hi> a ſure Houſe; ſo that his Houſe, Throne and Kingdom ſhall conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue for ever, to the worlds end, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7. <hi>viz.</hi> [in Chriſt his Divine Seed] as alſo in many other Scriptures, though in reſpect of <hi>Davids</hi> natural Race it was not ſo, (as he ſpeaks) 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 23.5. yet as a type for a long time his natural Race alſo proſpered into a Kingdom, as <hi>Ezekiel</hi> 16.13.</p>
            <p n="4">4. As all Promiſes to <hi>Abraham</hi> and his whole Seed were chiefly to and by that his one Divine Seed Chriſt, as <hi>Gal.</hi> 3. ſo alſo more eſpecially to all his ſpiritual Seed then. [See their many diſtinctions <hi>Reſurrect.</hi> p. 10, 11.] and likewiſe to <hi>Iſaac, Jacob</hi> and <hi>David,</hi> and to all their Spiritual Seed at the ſame time; and though the natural race of them all had for a time in <hi>Canaan</hi> a Typical, Conditional, Temporal, Changable intereſt, (which by ſin they all ſucceſſively loſt, <hi>Mich.</hi> 2.10.) yet <hi>Abraham, Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Jacob</hi> looked for that City and heavenly Countrey a far off, <hi>viz.</hi> [of a heavenly nature] whoſe Maker and Builder is God, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.16.40. for themſelves and all their ſpiritual Seed, at the firſt Reſurrection, (as by our paper of the Jews Converſion, is largely evident, <hi>pag.</hi> 5, 6.) <hi>Jacob</hi> alſo Propheſied of <hi>Judah's</hi> Dominion, <hi>Gen.</hi> 49. which was the Type of Chriſts, who was to deſcend from <hi>Judah,</hi> who is therefore in that ſtate ſtiled the Lion of the Tribe of <hi>Judah, Rev.</hi> 5. which Dominion of his and his Saints ſhall not be forfeited, nor paſs to other people, (as <hi>Daniel</hi> ſpeaks) when he ſhall ceaſe to ſit on his Fathers Throne, and come to ſit on his own Throne in the ſaid 1000 years with his Saints, <hi>Rev.</hi> 3.21. as the Son of <hi>David</hi> for ever, <hi>viz.</hi> while the world remains, 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 7. When will really be the ſure Mercies of <hi>David</hi> (as was ſaid) for himſelf and all his ſpiritual Seed, which are ſo many wayes diſtinguiſhed from the natural, (as ought to be well obſerved.) The Deſign of God in all the promiſed mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies to all thoſe Fathers, was, that their Race and State ſhould grow up or proſper in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a Kingdom, as was hinted before, <hi>Ezekiel</hi> 16.13. which their natural Race had only as a Type for a time conditionally; but it was ſurely confirmed to Chriſt in the
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:102127:6"/> renewed ſtate to come, when all the ſaid ſpiritual Seed ſhall riſe and reign with him, as is confirmed by all the Prophets, witneſſed to in the Goſpels and Apoſtles Writings, and carryed on by Chriſt himſelf from the beginning of the <hi>Revelation</hi> to the end thereof. And,</p>
            <p n="3">3. Hence alſo obſerve, that that perſonal comeing in the Clouds is ſo often ſpoken of in that moſt Divine Book, as <hi>chap</hi> 1.7. <hi>Behold he cometh with Clouds;</hi> the ſame comeing in time, with <hi>Daniel,</hi> 7.13, 14. to be fulfilled <hi>Rev</hi> 19 11. to the end, when the Lord God Omnipotent is ſaid to Reign, <hi>v.</hi> 6. and when the ſaid Saints ſhall alſo reign with him, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.4, 6. Again, to <hi>Philodelphia, ch.</hi> 3.11. is another, [Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold I come quickly,] again after the <hi>Revelation</hi> was given, and <hi>John</hi> commanded to leave it open, <hi>chap.</hi> 22.10 then, <hi>v.</hi> 12. he adjoyns another [Behold I come quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,] and my reward is with me, even the ſame reward, <hi>ch.</hi> 11.19. of whi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h the Spirit and the Bride alſo ſay, <hi>Come:</hi> which Chriſt again aſcertaineth, <hi>v.</hi> 20. ſaying, <hi>Surely I come quickly;</hi> and it is there once more implored by the Spirit in the Saints, <hi>even ſo come Lord Jeſus,</hi> v. 21. What man can then with reaſon, or ſhall dare, againſt ſo much evident Scripture, (without good Reaſon) to deny any of theſe, much more all of theſe ſo often repeated Texts reſpecting his ſaid comeing in the Clouds. Hence ſaith <hi>Jeremie</hi> of that time, <hi>ch.</hi> 3.17. <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> ſhall be called the Throne of the Lord, when alſo the Prophet <hi>Iſa.</hi> witneſſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>h, <hi>ch.</hi> 24.23. The Moon ſhall be confounded, and the Sun aſhamed, when the Lord of Hoſts ſhall reign in Mount <hi>Sion,</hi> and in <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> and before his Ancients gloriouſly: And <hi>Ezekiel</hi> ſtiles that City from that time it ſhall be ſet up, <hi>Jehovah Shamma, The Lord is there,</hi> ch. <hi>ult.</hi> v. <hi>ult.</hi> So <hi>Zachery,</hi> twice, <hi>ch.</hi> 2.10, 11. he will dwell in the middeſt of <hi>Sion;</hi> and <hi>Zephany, ch</hi> 3.13, 14. the King of <hi>Iſrael</hi> is in the middeſt of thee, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> with much illuſtration there obſerva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And <hi>Daniel</hi> ſhews punctually the beginning then of Chriſts ſaid univerſal and perpetual Kingdom, <hi>ch.</hi> 7. <hi>viz.</hi> when the Body of the Beaſt ſhall be given to the burning flame; of which ſtate ſpeak alſo all the reſt of the Prophets; (as in our <hi>Iren. ch.</hi> 5, 6, 7, 8.) and our 12 Foundations from <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15. to the end of the <hi>Revelati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on,</hi> [beſides what more was proved in <hi>Aſſert.</hi> 7. of our <hi>Key,</hi> and in other parts.]</p>
            <p n="3">3. Now as from the drift of all the ſaid Covenants, Promiſes and Propheſies, and all the ſaid parts of holy Scripture, his ſaid perſonal comeing, appearance and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, is evidently intended, (as is from them all manifeſt.)</p>
            <p>So the third head of Argumenrs do prove all the ſame to be perſonal will be from the Conſideration that at the ſaid comeing he will begin his great day of Judgment, ſtiled <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, the Judgment of the great day, <hi>Jude</hi> 6. when will be the <hi>Matu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinum Judicium,</hi> or the firſt Seſſion thereof, which the Jews from <hi>Dan.</hi> 7. uſed to ſtile יום דין or יום דינא רבא , the day of Judgment, or the great day of Judgment: Hence the Spirit of God aſcribes thereto all the peculiar marks and parts of a day of Judgment; as 1. The Judgment is ſet, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7.10. 2. The Books are o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pened, 3. The Quick. And 4. The Dead are Judged, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.1. and that at his appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance and Kingdom, or which is the ſame, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.19. when his Enemies are deſtroyed, and his Saints rewarded, and all the like marks and parts of that Judgment will be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain at the <hi>Veſpertinum Judicium,</hi> above 1000 years after, as is diſtinctly manifeſt, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.11. to the end, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Hence the deſtruction of <hi>Babylon</hi> is ſtiled the beginning of Revenges, <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.42. in <hi>Moſes</hi> hi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> ſong for Poſterity, upon which follows <hi>Daniels Matutinum Judicium,</hi> when the Body of the Beaſt ſhall be given to the burning flame: upon which the Prophetical ſong brings in the joyful union of Jews and Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles, as then to take place, <hi>viz.</hi> upon that execution of Vengeance, when Gods hand takes hold on Judgment, and makes his Arrows drunk in blood, when that enemy An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tichriſt ſhall be diſpatched out of the world, <hi>v.</hi> 40, 41.42. and the frequent expreſſion
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:102127:6"/> of Gods judging the Whore (then) ſuits thereunto, as <hi>ch.</hi> 19 2. upon the great Hal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lelujah then ſung for the ſame, <hi>v.</hi> 1. the like often in <hi>ch.</hi> 18. <hi>v.</hi> 8. ſtrong is the Lord that judgeth her, and <hi>v.</hi> 10. in one hour is thy judgment come: again, <hi>v.</hi> 19. in one hour is ſhe made deſolate: ſo <hi>v.</hi> 20 God hath avenged you of her, ye holy Apoſtles and Prophets, with much more to the end: and this Revenge is greatly encouraged, Reward her as ſhe hath rewarded you, and double her double, <hi>&amp;c. v.</hi> 6, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But as for the Beaſts ruine the Judgment is ſet, and the Books were opened, ſaith <hi>Daniel, ch.</hi> 7.10. and that was becauſe of the great words the Horn ſpake, <hi>v.</hi> 11. and the iſſue was the Body of the Beaſt is given to the burning flame at that time, when the Son of man comes in the Clouds of Heaven, <hi>v.</hi> 13, 14. and receives his ſaid Kingdom alſo, both thoſe parts, [of the morning Judgment] as <hi>Pſal.</hi> 49. are explained by Judgment, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.19. God is praiſed for then judging his Saints with reward, as well as judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Enemies with deſtruction: the manner of Execution is ſet forth at the <hi>Arma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geddon</hi> Battel, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19.11 ſo Gog and Magog both to be deſtroyed upon that Gods great day of Vengeance or Recompences, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 39.8. which in ſpecial is often in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſo called and deſcribed, as <hi>Iſa.</hi> 66. in many particulars, where alſo the Conver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion and Deliverance of the Jews are joined in that Propheſie with the deſtruction of the ſame Enemies at the great day of God Almighty (as it is called) <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.14, 16. as was ſaid before, from <hi>Deut.</hi> 32.41, 42, 43. Now when Chriſt comes to that Judgment in the morning of that great day, he will come perſonally, and all the time he will be in rewarding his Saints at the firſt bodily Reſurrection in his King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, and reign then, and in the New <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> ſtate then in the world he will be perſonally with them, and they ſhall then and there behold his glory which his Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther hath given him as Mediator, God man, <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.24. all the time he is raiſing of them to enjoy the happineſs of that ſtate (which Mr. <hi>Mede</hi> conceives will be in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing a great part of the 1000 years) who ſhall then enjoy the Viſion of his Perſon with them, who ſhall then be their happineſs and their glory: But the evidence of ſuch perſonal Judgment then will be farther confirmed from the particulars under the next head of Arguments drawn from the many actions or great things the Scripture ſpeaks of to be then done peculiarly by himſelf, and at that time.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Therefore to proceed to thoſe acts peculiar to Chriſt then to be done by him: The firſt is, he will bring his Saints with him then, as <hi>Zach.</hi> 14.5. [he will come and all the Saints with him] confirmed by St. <hi>Paul,</hi> he will come at his appearance with all his Saints, 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 3. <hi>ult.</hi> and 4.14 them alſo that ſleep in Jeſus will, God then bring with him, and therefore the Bride the Lambs Wife is ready when the Halelu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jahs are ſung, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19 7. which is expounded, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.9.10. to be the New <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> (then) come down from God out of Heaven, [or the ſpirits of juſt men before made perfect, <hi>Heb.</hi> 12. coming with Chriſt to receive their ſpiritual bodies in their order] whereby they are made capable of the happy Viſion of Chriſts Perſon, and of the many parts of the happineſs of that <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> ſtate, the Manſion for that time which Chriſt went to prepare for them in ſpecial, <hi>Joh.</hi> 14.1, 2. (as his own <hi>Revelation</hi> re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolves us) but whether it will after be tranſlated with them, when the created Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vens and Earth ſhall be diſſolved, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20.11. we find nothing to reſolve us: but that an infinite and eternal happineſs will follow the end of that great day of Judgment, upon their final ſentence of Abſolution and Approbation is there, and in many other Scriptures manifeſt; where God hath prepared it for them for ever, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And as he will then bring all his ſuffering Saints from <hi>Abel,</hi> to that time he cometh to that Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, with him.</p>
            <p>So, 2. He will raiſe their Bodies to make them capable of the happineſs of that ſtate, as one great end of his bringing them (then) with him; and being ſuch a Mercy
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:102127:7"/> as is founded upon all the Covenants and promiſed Mercies we ſpake of before, belong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the Father and their ſpiritual Seed, in the renewed ſtate of the world, ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed by the Father for him and them together, as was ſhewed before, whence farther evidences of his perſonal preſence with them, are very evident, and cogent from Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, if God work that Faith in men to believe them upon ſuch Scripture grounds; and it is only Chriſts peculiar perſonal work then to raiſe the Saints departed, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. When he comes in the Clouds then, and converts the Jews, they ſhall perſonally ſee him through the Clouds, [without which, mortal eyes could not behold the brightneſs of his Glory at his appearance] therefore often ſo called, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, &amp; <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, his appearance, and the appearance of his preſence, who will then be manifeſt to be the only Potentate, King of Kings, and Lord of Lords, as the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> divinely and fully teacheth, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.14, 15, 16. and as Chriſt alſo in due or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der reveals largely, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19. with many wonderful expreſſions of his Excellency then to be manifeſt; but that the Jews that pierced him, and every eye [then capable] ſhall ſee him, the Clouds ſhall then wait upon him, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1.7. it is ſet forth as a great wonder, Behold; he cometh [with Clouds] as the Holy Spirit therefore ſpeaks, and with an addition of [even ſo Amen,] as being the time of fulfilling of promiſed Mercies to Jews and faithful Gentiles, the ſpiritual Children of <hi>Abraham</hi> by Faith, (as the Apoſtle ſpeaks, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.29.) yea and they are ſaid to be Chriſts ſeed too, which he ſhall then ſee upon ſuch prolonging of his days in the world then, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53. now when all thoſe ſhall with their Eyes ſee him, he muſt then neceſſarily be perſonally preſent: and this is according to the main intent of <hi>Zach.</hi> 12.10. to the end; of the Jews great Converſion; [for all Revelations from the ſounding of the ſeventh Trumpet at Chriſts coming in the Clouds refer us to the Propheſies of the Old Te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtament] who have this Key given to open all that follows there to the end: [that the Teſtimony of Jeſus is the Spirit of Propheſie, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19 10. for he there witneſſeth nothing but what his own holy Spirit had taught in ſome meaſure before by his Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets: So <hi>Zach.</hi> 3.9 their iniquity ſhall be taken away in one day, and <hi>Iſa.</hi> 6 8, 9. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that Nation ſhall be born in one day, <hi>&amp;c</hi> which their <hi>Elias</hi> to be ſent, (ſome time before, as <hi>Mal.</hi> 4.1.) to guide them in ſeeking their promiſed land then, ſeems to prepare for towards the end of <hi>Daniels</hi> 1335 years, <hi>c.</hi> 11, 12.</p>
            <p>And 4. Likewiſe the fulfilling of that Propheſie, <hi>Zach.</hi> 14. when his feet ſhall ſtand on Mount <hi>Olivet,</hi> from whence he aſcended; upon which, it is very probable, he will again then deſcend [with Clouds] wonderfully cauſing it then to cleave aſunder, and cauſe the Valley to <hi>Azal;</hi> ſutable to what thoſe two Angels ſaid to the Apoſtles when he aſcended, <hi>Acts</hi> 1.11. and there is much in that whole Chapter of <hi>Zach.</hi> 1. to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of theſe purpoſes, but we muſt in this buſineſs in hand briefly only point at many things of ſuch nature: and ſuch wonderful works of Chriſt ſeem to prepare that ſo long hardned people the Jews for the wonder of Chriſts mercy to be then magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied towards them, according to many great Propheſies, as <hi>Ezek.</hi> 36, and 37. <hi>ch.</hi> and as in our ſaid Paper of their Converſion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and his ſtanding on Mount <hi>Olivet,</hi> and its cleaving then, alſo clearly prove him preſent.</p>
            <p n="5">5. His Command to bring his great Enemies, and ſlay them before him, <hi>Luke</hi> 19. proveth his preſence when it ſhall be done; and that will be at the Judgment of the Beaſt, <hi>Dan.</hi> 7. and upon or at the deſtruction of Gog, the Turk, <hi>Dan.</hi> 11.45. for <hi>ch.</hi> 10.1. at that time ſtands up <hi>Michael,</hi> the Prince of <hi>Daniels</hi> people, when he tells him his people ſhall be delivered, and when theſe Enemies periſh [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, it is done] at the laſt Vial, <hi>Rev.</hi> 16.16, 17. which fulfils that great Prophecy of Gogs and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogs deſtruction, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 39.8. at that great day which the Lord God there ſpake of, as <hi>pag.</hi> 61, 62. of <hi>Reſtit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="6">
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:102127:7"/>6. The binding of Satan then, and ſealing him up in the bottomleſs pit, <hi>Rev.</hi> 20. when he eminently breaks the Serpents head, as <hi>Gen.</hi> 3.15. at the end of his ſitting on his Fathers right hand, when he will make his temporal or corporal enemies, together with his ſpiritual (eminently) his footſtool, which is alſo an act ſuitable only to Chriſts Soveraignty then which he will exerciſe (as the Father ſet down in the Book with 7 Seals) for 1000 years; and in the little ſpace afterwards, when alſo upon Satans laſt moſt wicked attempt of Rebellion againſt his Divine Soveraign Authority, he and all his ſhall periſh for ever, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="7">7. His diſpenſing of his Rewards to his Saints then will be his peculiar perſonal act (as he ſpeaketh expreſsly) at his ſaid perſonal comeing, <hi>Rev.</hi> 22.12. Behold I come quickly, and my Reward is with me; and ſo he judgeth his Saints with Reward, <hi>ch.</hi> 11.19. and this he will be doing all the 1000 years for them.</p>
            <p n="8">8. His ſitting on the Throne of his Father <hi>David, Luke</hi> 1.32. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 9. not as he ſits now on God the Fathers Throne, but as diſtinct from it, <hi>Rev</hi> 3.21. when he comes from his Fathers right hand to ſit on his own Throne in the world, as the Son of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid,</hi> and be manifeſt therein to be the King of Kings, and Lord of Lords, and all his manifold actings in righteouſneſs and Judgment in the Earth: of which are many and great Propheſies (then) upon his ſaid Morning Judgment in all the 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>00 years, alſo prove his perſonal preſence, as the Branch, or one out of the root of <hi>Jeſſe;</hi> and yet though ſo the Son, yet as God he was the root of <hi>David, Rev.</hi> 5. But <hi>[N. B.]</hi> not as ſome miſtake of his and his Saints being (then) as other Kings and men in the world, but comeing as the great God, <hi>Tit.</hi> 2.13. in his own, and his Fathers, and his Angels glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and in that Chriſtalline, Tranſparent Golden, Wonderful, Holy and Belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved New <hi>Jeruſalem, Rev.</hi> 21. 1500 miles high, as well as 1500 miles long and broad, a perfect Cube, without allegoriſing of it, or many other matters then and there [for Gods Spirit hath not ſaid it will be of ſuch height in vain] who beſt knows, (and being likewiſe the Maker and Builder of that City for the Fathers, and all his Saints, as <hi>Heb.</hi> 11.16.40.) is able to make it both capacious enough, and ſuitably glorious to the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed holy raiſed Saints condition, therein to behold Chriſts glory, <hi>Joh.</hi> 17.24. their bleſſed Redeemer, Head and Husband; and when men begin to wait upon God more duly to ſeek to know theſe things from his Word (as they are there held out) in humility and uprightneſs, he will doubtleſs give them a ſuitable Faith to believe more of ſuch Divine Truths, which is now a great duty (though the Old Seducer labours by all means poſſible to perſwade men to the contrary) otherwiſe, like <hi>Thomas,</hi> they may not (haply) know them until they ſee them; and (haply) for wilful neglect may then obtain a ſmaler portion in them, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But all the ſaid promiſed mercies ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded by Chriſt (as is manifeſt in our <hi>Scheme</hi>) do refer to that time and ſtate, and will then have their due accompliſhments (though multitudes now ſhut their eyes a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt ſuch light) as by our ſix Concluſions is ſufficiently evident, <hi>pag.</hi> 17, 18. of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitut.</hi>) ſuch glorious Revelations left by the Father to be made known by his Son a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone, after all, ought earneſtly to be ſought into by all good means, and highly prized when they are found: The tranſparent matter of thoſe Coeleſtial Spheres wherein thoſe glorious lights above us ſhine unto the world is not by men diſcoverable what it is; ſo neither is the matter of that glorious City prepared by God himſelf for that King of glory and his ſaid Saints in that bleſſed ſtate, farther known then, as we are informed from the holy Scriptures concerning the ſame: and though the raiſed Saints, and thoſe then in the natural life, will then be of one Communion, yet their ſtates otherwiſe, ſeem to be pointed out much to differ, [as by <hi>Ezekiels</hi> New <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> and St. <hi>Johns</hi> may appear, the one for the Converred Jews with the Gentiles to walk in the light of the other, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.24. the other peculiar to the raiſed Saints. And,</p>
            <p n="9">
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:102127:8"/>9. From the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi>'s expreſſions to the <hi>Theſſalonians,</hi> 2 Epiſt. 1.10. there will be at Chriſts ſaid comeing (as he there tells them) much occaſion of glorifying him by his Saints, and of his being admired then by all that believe, as well for his Perſonal Excellencies, as for all his ſaid actions in thoſe times, which without his Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal Preſence, they would not have opportunity and occaſion then to do.</p>
            <p>The laſt Head of Arguments for ſuch Chriſts Perſonal Preſence then, will be from the Relation he then ſtands in to his ſaid Saints: Firſt, he will be then the Saints viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Head, and they his viſible Members, both to be preſent. 2. At the Marriage of the Lamb, he will be the Bridegroom, and the Saints his viſible Bride, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.9. now that Relation imports his perſonal appearance as well as hers.</p>
            <p n="3">3. As the Husband he will long continue in that ſtate with them, and dwell with them the ſaid 1000 years: therefore upon the comeing of the ſaid New <hi>Jeruſalem, [viz.</hi> the Inhabitants metanimically] down with him from God out of Heaven (there) the Holy Spirit declares, That the Tabernacle of God, <hi>viz.</hi> the body which he Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacled in before for a little time, then will be with men; ſo as to dwell with them that long ſeaſon, and therefore perſonally preſent.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The joint intereſt that Chriſt and his ſaid Saints will have in the happineſs of that ſtate, as heirs and joint-heirs with him thereof; which alſo prove his perſonal preſence, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21 7.</p>
            <p n="5">5. More eſpecially their Reigning with him on earth then, as the moſt comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſive Mercy of all the reſt, which all the other tend to make up, [as the proſpering into a Kingdom was to the Natural Race in the Type, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 16.13.] and hence this Kingdom and Reign of the Saints with Chriſt is ſo often mentioned in the <hi>Revelation:</hi> For then the Kings Daughter that is all glorious within, wh ſe Garments are ſaid to be of wrought Gold, ſhall enter into the Kings Palace, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 45. who ſhall make of her Children Princes in all Lands: ſome (as Chriſt ſaid) over two, or five, or ten Cities, <hi>Luke</hi> 19. and all ſuch offices and Relations ſpeak his perſonal preſence in that ſtate, when once theſe everlaſting Gates ſhall begin to ſtand open for the King of Glory to enter in, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 24.</p>
            <p>And thus much at preſent briefly of Chriſts ſaid perſonal Comeing and Reign in the 1000 years, as proved abundantly from all the fore named Conſiderations.</p>
            <p>Now the <hi>Second</hi> thing, <hi>viz.</hi> That they ſhall be about 20 years hence from this 76, or rather 80, which we deſire to give farther ſatisfaction in according to what we find in the Word of God, and from ſuch Divine Grounds as are according thereunto; upon which our Belief thereof is founded, are theſe enſuing.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In general we find all Prophetick Scripture is almoſt fulfilled neer to Chriſts ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance, as in particulars may hereafter appear.</p>
            <p n="2">2. More eſpecially, becauſe <hi>Daniel</hi>'s 2300 years given by <hi>Palmoni,</hi> or the ſecret Numberer, <hi>ch.</hi> 8. which many ways are manifeſt; 1. To be the moſt certain Number or Meaſure of the years of the <hi>Jews</hi> Bondage, and of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> Dominion, through all their four Monarchies And, 2. The Meaſure of both his other Numbers in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nexion with the <hi>Revelation</hi> Numbers joyntly; which admirably terminate in the ſame Period with it, at Chriſt's ſaid appearance, when in all thoſe reſpects that Number will be fulfilled, as follows.</p>
            <p>For the <hi>Firſt,</hi> That it is the Meaſure of the <hi>Jews</hi> Bondage, and of the <hi>Gentiles</hi> Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minion, is proved largely from the Context of <hi>ch.</hi> 8. and by many other reaſons in our <hi>Summary</hi> of <hi>Daniel, p.</hi> 6, 7.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Becauſe the experience of that threefold Overturning of <hi>David</hi>'s Kingdom, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 21.26, 27. until he come whoſe right it is, and which God hath there promiſed to give him (then) are almoſt compleated, by experimental fulfilling, as we ſhewed,
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:102127:8"/> 
               <hi>Introduction</hi> pag. 9, 10. which (very probably) will be fulfilled at the ſame period.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It conſiſts of two evident parts, very admirably concurring with the joynt times of <hi>Daniel</hi> and the <hi>Revelation, viz.</hi> Of the firſt part of 600 years from the Captivity of <hi>Babylon,</hi> in the beginning of the fourth year of <hi>Jehojakim,</hi> and the firſt of <hi>Nebuchad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nezzar, Anno Mundi</hi> 3398. about three years before 3400. which therefore will be out ſo much before Chriſts Birth at 4000. as Biſhop <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher</hi> Computes it, (when 37 years more ended <hi>Daniels</hi> Weeks) from whence alſo are reckoned 1700 years of <hi>Revelation</hi> Propheſie to Chriſts ſaid appearance, at the Deſtruction of the laſt, or <hi>Roman</hi> Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchy, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.10. of both <hi>Ezekiels</hi> Gog and Magog at the ſame time, <hi>ch.</hi> 39.6, 7, 8. which two numbers make up the 2300. <hi>Dan.</hi> 8. [of the latter number more after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards.]</p>
            <p n="2">2. Again it is alſo manifeſt to be the meaſure of both the other myſtical numbers in <hi>Dan.</hi> 9. and <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.12. in connexion with the <hi>Revelation</hi> Numbers reaching to the ſame period; all being the dictates of the Eternal, All-knowing, &amp; All-working Lord the Spirit: whoſe Epochaes being many hundred years diſtant, yet exactly agree in the ſame Period, the ſame glorious Divine evidence of Truth being carryed on by them all, both of the Jews deliverance, and the Enemies ſaid Ruine, at Chriſts ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance, as was ſaid.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Of the 70 Weeks, <hi>Dan.</hi> 9. or 490 years from the 20th of <hi>Artaxerxes Longiomanus, Neh.</hi> 2.1. <hi>An. Mund.</hi> 3550. at the execution of the Decree for Building the City <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> until the three years and an half ending <hi>Daniels</hi> laſt Week, <hi>An Dom.</hi> 37. after Chriſts Birth, in the middle of which laſt Week Chriſt hy his Death put an end to Tranſgreſſion, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> and by his Reſurrection brought in everlaſting Righteouſneſs; and at his Aſcention triumphed gloriouſly over the ſpiritual Principalities and Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, <hi>Coll.</hi> 2.15. when alſo began the Kingdom of the Stone, <hi>Dan.</hi> 2.44. for that 1666<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> years to his Deſcending again, in that interim to break and conſume the Dragon and the Beaſt, until about the end of 1700 years from Chriſts Birth, when it will become the Kingdom of the Mountain, filling the whole Earth at Chriſts ſecond comeing.</p>
            <p>And, 2. For that Divine Mark or Diſcovery of taking away Sacrifice, (ultimately) given to <hi>Daniel</hi> by the ſame Lord the Spirit, above 800 years before it came to paſs, when his 1335 years, <hi>ch.</hi> 12 12. ſhould reach to the ſaid bleſſed times, which was eventu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally manifeſt, by Gods Wonder-working Providence and Power, about <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 365. againſt the provoking Abominations of <hi>Julian</hi> the Apoſtate Emperour, who not only in oppoſition to Jeſus Chriſt ſet up many Heathen Idolatries, but incouraged the Jews to build their Temple for Sacrifice, granting allowance for the ſame out of the publick Treaſury: But when they had layed Foundations for the Temple, and multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes came to ſee the Workmens proceedings (as many Hiſtorians relate) Gods wrath was manifeſt againſt them by Fire and Earthquakes, and the like terrible appearances thereof, killing many Workmen,<note place="margin">Amianus Marcel. Socrat. Zozamen. Theodoret, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </note> with ſuch as came to ſee the ſame; burn'd their very Tools, or melted them, and caſt out the very ſtones layed in the ground for Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, occaſioning <hi>Cyrill,</hi> then Biſhop there, to ſay <hi>Now is fulfilled our Saviours Prediction, One ſtone ſhall not be left upon another that ſhall not be thrown down,</hi> &amp;c. From which time we read no more of the Jews publick Sacrificing: and that time wonderfully fits the ſaid Mark; for 1335. being added to 365. make up like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe 1300. to the ſaid bleſſed time, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Whereunto,</p>
            <p n="4">4. We may annex thoſe 45 years of the Jews laſt troublous times, <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.1. from the 1290. years in <hi>v.</hi> 11. unto 1335. in <hi>v</hi> 12. (when the bleſſed times begin) the former ſaid 365. years till <hi>Julian,</hi> being added to them, which ſo together make up
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:102127:9"/> as was ſaid) 1700 years from Chriſts Birth to his ſecond comeing, which we obſerved in our late Addreſs to the Kings Majeſty, to be now a ſpecial Alarm to this World: In theſe words, [Of the neer approach of whoſe ſaid comeing (I conceive) the world of late years hath been ſufficiently alarm'd, by the Jews attempt (in that ſeaſon) to ſeek their promiſed Land, 45 years before that his ſecond comeing, (as appears from <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.11, 12.) and (as is very obſervable) in that type thereof <hi>Joſhua, ch.</hi> 14, 7.10. in that ſo very apt decyphering of our Jeſus now; which (whatever others think of it) I have much pondered ſince in my heart, from Gods former like myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious proce dings, when he is about to do great things in the world, and of which I now underſtand an uſeful book is written, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>]</p>
            <p n="5">5. The Beaſts Date of 42 moneths, with the Sack-cloth Witneſſes 1260. years, and the Womans time, times and half a time [being all contemporaries] now ready almoſt to expire, as in <hi>Reſtit.</hi> p. 57, 58. &amp; p. 74, 75. not long before the VVhores Burning, <hi>Rev</hi> 18. which muſt precede the utter deſtruction of the man of Sin at Chriſts ſaid ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance, 2 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.8. at Gods ſure number of 1666. counted (as appears) by his own Divine wiſdom of <hi>Daniels</hi> ſaid numbers, and St. <hi>Pauls</hi> Doctrine from Chriſts aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cending, to his deſcending with Clouds about 20 years hence, as before.</p>
            <p n="6">6. The Turks day, hour, moneth and year, <hi>viz.</hi> 396. years, <hi>Rev.</hi> 9.11. being the ſixth Trumpet, or ſecond VVoe beginning about <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 1300. or little after, in the Ottaman Family, whoſe ſaid 396 years will be compleated about the ſame time, as in <hi>Reſtit.</hi> pag. 74.</p>
            <p n="7">7. The probable proceedings of the Vials under the ſaid ſixth Trumpet to prepare for the ruine of the Beaſt about the end of the ſixth Vial, when <hi>Ezekiels</hi> ſaid Gog and Magog, <hi>viz.</hi> Turk and Pope are like to periſh neer in time together.</p>
            <p n="8">8. The Table of the bad times, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11. to verſe 15. [referring to both <hi>Revelation</hi> Schemes of the Civil and Eccleſiaſtical ſtate of <hi>Rome</hi>] (as in our ſhort Scheme of the whole <hi>Revelation</hi> is manifeſt) for about 1700 years from Chriſts Birth, or three years before, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. Of the Civil ſtate to the Red Dragons caſting down to the earth by <hi>Conſtantine</hi> the great, about <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 320. and that other, <hi>viz.</hi> the Chriſtian Emperours, for a ſhort ſpace, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.10. for about 100 years after, and then the Inroades of the Bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous Nations upon the VVeſtern Empire in the four firſt Trumpets breaking the Empire, [to prepare for the ten Kings to follow, who ſhould give their power to the Beaſt, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>.] diſſolving the Senate, ſacking and burning the City, and plucking the laſt Emperour <hi>Auguſtulus</hi> (as it is ſtoryed) out of his Throne, which were ſo many milder blaſts of Gods wrath, for the Dragons (or Heathen Emperours) Perſecutions of the Saints before (as is very probable) for about 200 years to about <hi>An. Dom.</hi> 600. or after; from which time the two following more terrible VVoe-Trum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pets of the <hi>Saracens</hi> and <hi>Turks, ch.</hi> 9. have for above 1000. years more proceeded to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ecute the more terrible wrath of God upon the Eaſtern <hi>Roman</hi> Empire, until at the end of the ſecond VVoe, or at the beginning of the ſeventh Trumpet, or third VVoe, the whole Empire, according to <hi>Balaams</hi> Propheſie, <hi>Numb.</hi> 24.24. ſhall periſh for ever, or as St. <hi>John</hi> expreſſeth the ſame thing, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17.12. ſhall go into perdition then.</p>
            <p>So, 2. For the true Churches regular ſtate meaſured, <hi>Rev.</hi> 11.1. until the Beaſts time, when ſhe was ſaid to have the Moon under her feet; and in reſpect of her ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering ſtate until then, and for that little time under <hi>Conſtantine</hi> and <hi>Theodoſius</hi> reigns, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> after which by Hereſies her ſufferings returned, as by the Dragons flood, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> until about 420. or more, when it appears the ſaid Beaſts 42. moneths for his treading un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der foot the holy City began, with the ſaid two Sack-cloth VVitneſſes, 1260. dayes of years, and the ſaid VVomans VVilderneſs ſtate, all to end before the VVhore of <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bylons</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:102127:9"/> burning, and a little (as appears) before the ſaid Beaſts laſt deſtruction, at the <hi>Armageddon</hi> Battle, <hi>Rev.</hi> 16. ſaid to be the great day of God Almighty, from <hi>Ezek.</hi> 39.8. and to be executed, as <hi>Rev.</hi> 18. &amp; 19 <hi>ch.</hi> And do not theſe myſtical diſcove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries now alſo concur with thoſe more noted marks of our Saviour, that iniquity ſhould abound, and the love of many ſhould wax cold? and do not St <hi>Peters</hi> Atheiſtical ſcoffers at true Religion in theſe times plainly ſhew themſelves? and doth not the prevalency of Profaneneſs, and of the abominable wickedneſs of the ſoul and unclean ſpirit alſo ſadly appear in theſe dayes, and openly and ſhameleſsly manifeſt them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, whoſe great endeavour hath been <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in the latter times, 1 Tim. 4.1. to ſet up the name of Chriſt againſt the Doctrine of Chriſt, as reſpecting the judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment: So <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, in theſe laſt dayes, 2 <hi>Tim</hi> 3.1. by a form of his Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to obſtruct the power thereof in the VVitneſſes of it, as reſpecting the affections, and by ſuch a tw<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>-fold Antichriſtianiſme to promote by degrees any, even the worſt of evils, <hi>Rev.</hi> 13.17. <hi>Eſa.</hi> 66.5: from all which evidences and the like, all ſerious and judicious perſons may eaſily (upon due conſideration) diſcern that our ſaid belief of the neer approach of Chriſts ſaid appearance hath many Divine Foundations, laid by the Spirit of God, in holy Scripture, to reſt it ſelf upon: in all ſuch wayes of Diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very as the moſt wiſe and gracious God hath been pleaſed in ſome latitude, to make known to us although neither the day nor hour, [nor yet the moneth or year] can by man be determined. I might have added want of Faith of theſe things, as in <hi>Aſſert.</hi> 10. of our <hi>Key.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hence let all vain, Worldly, Prophane, and Unregenerate Perſons be admoniſhed ſpeedily to ſeek the Lords Face, by true Converſion unto him by Faith and Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, before that little ſpace be ſpent, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. Let all real Saints act firſt more earneſtly, in ſtudying Unity in all that is truly good, avoiding unneceſſary Dividing Principles and Practiſes.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Be much in the exerciſe of ſincere piety in the ſight of the heart ſearching God, and labour to promote it in others, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. Be more earneſtly exerciſed in Charitable works, 1. For the good of the ſouls; 2. For the good of the bodies and perſons of all ſorts and condit ons of men. And,</p>
            <p n="5">5. Labour to exerciſe very great moderation in all worldly and temporal now fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding things.</p>
            <p>And, Laſtly, Let all men be admoniſhed not to deceive themſelves or others with a groundleſs expectation of ſuch an excellent and happy ſpiritual Church-ſtate and times before that world to come at Chriſts ſaid appearance (ſave what may (ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time) be upon the finiſhing the Aſcention of the ſlain Witneſſes) But until that new ſtate begin we ſpake of, the obſtinacy of the Jews, and prophane Apoſtacy of the Gentiles are like in the general to obſtruct ſuch ſaid Expectations, until at Chriſts ſecond comeing they be powerfully and graciouſly removed, according to the many ancient Promiſes and Propheſies.</p>
            <p>But all judicious perſons may hence obſerve upon many evident Foundations laid down briefly in our <hi>Introduct.</hi> with this Appendix to it, how all the ſaid Curious work in Chriſts Divine Key doth admirably inform us in theſe three things, <hi>viz.</hi> in the <hi>quo,</hi> the <hi>quando,</hi> the <hi>quandiu;</hi> all reſpecting that time and ſtate: the firſt the <hi>[quo]</hi> two wayes; 1. As to the predictions of what is then to take place privatively for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moving of evils: And, 2. Poſitively, as to the performance of promiſed mercies to the Fathers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> 2. For the <hi>[quando]</hi> when they ſhall begin (as by this Appendix is many wayes manifeſt) namely, at the Beaſts and Gogs laſt ruine, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 39.8. and at the laſt Vial; for then [<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>] it is done; when Satan is to be bound and Chriſt will begin to reign with his Saints at the Renovation of all things <hi>Rev.</hi> 21.5. in his
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:102127:10"/> Mediatory or Davidical Kingdom for that 1000. years, of which largly, <hi>Reſtit.</hi> p. 61, 62. And, 3. For the <hi>[quandiu]</hi> eſpecially obſerve, how Divinely, and wonderfully exact Chriſts Determination thereof is, (as was ſhewed) for 1000. years moſt plainly: [for years in Scripture are alwayes litterally taken, though moneths, and weeks, and dayes were in this book before uſed often Prophetically] &amp; the whole number of 1000. is never uſed but for it ſelf (as <hi>Pareus</hi> obſerves) and both of them are here three times applyed both poſitively and relatively: Firſt, poſitively, to Satans binding, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, a thouſand years; and then Relatively, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, thoſe thouſand years, <hi>v.</hi> 2, 3. 2. So to the ſuffering Saints Reſurrection they reigned with Chriſt 1000 years, but the reſt of the dead lived not until thoſe thouſand years were ended, <hi>v.</hi> 4, 5. 3. So again to illuſtrate the happineſs of that their eſtate for that long time; 1. They are ſaid to be Bleſſed. 2. Holy. 3. Secured. 4. Highly honoured to be Prieſts to God and Chriſt. 5. Inveſted with Sovereign Authority, and that with Chriſt all that while Satan is bound; <hi>v:</hi> 6, 7. Theſe Scripture Truths are ſo wonderfully illuſtrated and Authoriſed by God the Father, Chriſt and the Holy Spirit, as no other part of the Goſpel is; and how men will henceforward, to whom theſe things are repreſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, be able to anſwer their not owning of them with the Truths annexed to them, (as in our ſix Concluſions, <hi>Reſtit.</hi> p. 17, 18, 19.) I know not: God grant they may duly weigh the ſame aforehand, and render the due glory to Chriſt for theſe Divine Truths reſpecting the Goſpel of his ſaid Kingdom, and the glorious excellencies and happineſs thereof for his ſaid ſuffering Saints ſhortly to take place. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="conclusion">
            <p>HEnce two of his Majeſties very conſiderable Queſtions may ſtrongly be reſolved; namely, 1. That the <hi>Roman</hi> Monarchy, <hi>viz.</hi> the Feet and Toes thereof in the two-fold Beaſt [the Papacy] will end about 20 years hence, at Chriſts Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pearance, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And,</p>
            <p n="2">2. That it appears from <hi>Daniels</hi> Numbers; That at the end of his 70 Weeks, <hi>ch.</hi> 9. the Kingdom of the Stone begins, about Chriſts Aſcention, (when he Triumphed Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritually) to continue 1666. years to the ſame period, with the ſaid 2300. <hi>Dan.</hi> 8. and with divers others ſaid Numbers, when Chriſts viſible and glorious Triumph will be in the world over all his great Enemies therein by making them his footſtool.</p>
            <p>To the third material Queſtion we ſhall add, That all the time from Chriſts firſt comeing to his ſecond, is ſet forth by the laſt times in ſacred Scripture, not only as was then ſaid in reference to that uſual expreſion in the Old Teſtament באחרית-הימים in the latter, or poſtremity of days; as <hi>Jacobs</hi> applying it to <hi>Shiloe's</hi> coming, <hi>Gen</hi> 49. &amp; <hi>Jeremies</hi> to the Jews Converſion at his ſecond comeing; <hi>c.</hi> 30. <hi>ult.</hi> and ſo of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten alſo to many things in the interim betwixt both: and the like is obſervable of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niels</hi> בעת קצ in the time of the end, which is the ſame with the times of the Goſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pel, as <hi>Dan.</hi> 11.36, 37, 38, 39, 40. and <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.4, 9. which times Chriſt in the <hi>Revelation</hi> divides into theſe three of the Dragon or Heathen Emperours. 2. Of the two-fold Beaſt or Papacy; and 3. Of his own Kingdom in the World the 1000 years, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In page 16. line 4. of <hi>Introduct.</hi> read <hi>Prieſtly,</hi> not <hi>Prophetical.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:102127:10"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
